Guide to the Botts Collection of LGBT History
University of Houston Libraries
Botts Collection of LGBT History
1973-2014
1985-2005
11/2015-017
Botts, Charles; Criscione, Larry; Harrington, Eugene; Hatlen, Leif; Lasher, Ralph
11.00 linear feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
This collection includes Resurrection Metropolitan Community Church (RMCC) documents, as well as photographs and a film of Ralph Lasher. The collection includes RMCC’s financial and administrative documents, as well as flyers and advertisements. It also includes documents from religious conferences and exercises.
Biographical Information:
In the 1970s, Charles Botts began collecting, preserving, and archiving documents, publications, and other items of historical significance to the lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender (LGBT) communities of Houston, southeast Texas, and the United States. He did so informally and eventually under the roof of the Resurrection Metropolitan Community Church (RMCC) of Houston, Texas. Mr. Botts amassed a significant collection of items related to the LGBT community and its history. Upon his death in 1994, a handful of dedicated volunteers continued Charles Botts’ work. Larry Criscione became active at this time and is primarily responsible for the expansion of the collection. A great effort was made to assure that the collection is accessible and useful to students, researchers, and journalists needing access to this unique body of information. The volunteers have also put together displays from the materials for numerous functions, in order to educate the public on different aspects of LGBT History.
In 2001 tropical storm Allison flooded large portions of Houston. The church library including the LGBT material collected by Charles Botts were affected as was everything in the church. It was after this storm that Leif Hatlen became involved with the collection. Due to water damage caused by the storm, some of the library materials was destroyed, much of the rest of the materials was water damaged and any system of filing or sorting was lost. Leif began to re-sort the materials, developing lists and indexes in the process. Later in 2005, Mike Kelley (now deceased) began to volunteer with the collection and developed computerized indexes that has been used for the magazines and to organize the individual collections.
In 2011, when it became apparent that Resurrection church’s goals and intentions with respect to the collection differed from those of the volunteers, Larry Criscione formed and incorporated the Botts Collection of Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual and Transgender History, Inc. (Botts Collection). The organization moved to a new location and continues collecting and cataloging items of historical importance to the region’s LGBT community.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Genre/Form of Material:
Correspondence; Photographs
Acquisition Information:
Donated by the Botts Collection of LGBT History, Inc.
Accruals:
Additional materials will be donated to the collection.
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes Resurrection Metropolitan Community Church (RMCC) documents, as well as photographs and a film of Ralph Lasher. The collection includes RMCC’s financial and administrative documents, as well as flyers and advertisements. It also includes documents from religious conferences and exercises. The photo collection documents the lives of Ralph Lasher and his partner, as well as events at RMCC and in the Houston LGBT community. Also included are the awards and plaques of Eugene Harrington.
Detailed List of Contents
- Ralph Lasher Collection
  - Noche Espiritual Pamphlets (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Prints and clippings (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - My Offering' envelope book (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Pictures and clippings (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Noche Espiritual Pamphlets (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Gospel of Thomas (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - World AIDS Day Service (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Publications (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - OutSmart Magazines (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - OutSmart Clippings (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Project Noah Papers (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "The Gay Harvest" Publication (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Resurrection MCC Board of Directors Meeting Papers (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - MCCR Congregational Meeting Minutes (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - MCCR Home Groups Minutes (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Memorial Book (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Book of Memories (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Binder 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Binder Share the Miracle (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - MCCR Policy Template (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Archives (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Option A Materials (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Preprinted Campaign Materials (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Camera-Ready Artwork (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Discover the Joy Binder (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Budgets with a Mission Second Edition (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - The Abingdon Guide to Building Ministry (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 1997 Compensation Handbook for Church Staff (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Stewardship Materials (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Program Overview VHS (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Budget Requests 1994 (Box 2, Folder 14-17)
  - Financial 1986 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Teachers Asking Long (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Budget Figures (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - GLYP, 2010 (Box 3, Item 1)
  - Gay and Lesbian Yellow Pages, 2000 (Box 3, Item 2)
  - Gay and Lesbian Yellow Pages, 2002 (Box 3, Item 3)
  - Gay and Lesbian Yellow Pages, 2003-2004 (Box 3, Item 4)
  - Gay and Lesbian Yellow Pages, 2008-2009 (Box 3, Item 5)
  - Gay and Lesbian Yellow Pages, 2001 (Box 3, Item 6)
  - Gay and Lesbian Yellow Pages, 2005 (Box 3, Item 7)
  - Gay and Lesbian Yellow Pages, 2006 (Box 3, Item 8)
  - Gay and Lesbian Yellow Pages, 2004-2005 (Box 3, Item 9)
  - Gay and Lesbian Yellow Pages, 2006-2007 (Box 3, Item 10)
  - Gay and Lesbian Yellow Pages, Summer 2007 (Box 3, Item 11)
  - Gay and Lesbian Yellow Pages, Winter 2007 (Box 3, Item 12)
  - The Bayou Book, 2002 (Box 3, Item 13)
  - The Bayou Book, 2003 (Box 3, Item 14)
  - GLYP, 2013-2014 (Box 3, Item 15)
  - GLYP, 2011-2012 (Box 3, Item 16)
  - Rainbow Pages, 2009 (Box 3, Item 17)
  - Rainbow Pages, 2011 (Box 3, Item 18)
  - Rainbow Pages, 2012 (Box 3, Item 19)
  - Rainbow Pages, 2005 (Box 3, Item 20)
  - Rainbow Pages, 2006 (Box 3, Item 21)
  - Rainbow Pages, 2007 (Box 3, Item 22)
  - Gay and Lesbian Yellow Pages, 1994-1995 (Box 3, Item 23)
  - Gay and Lesbian Yellow Pages, 1992-1993 (Box 3, Item 24)
  - GLYP, 2011-2013 (Box 3, Item 25)
  - Austin Gay & Lesbian Yellow Pages, 2000-2001 (Box 3, Item 26)
  - Dallas Gay & Lesbian Yellow Pages, 2004-2005 (Box 3, Item 27)
  - New York Gay & Lesbian Yellow Pages, 2000-2001 (Box 3, Item 28)
  - Austin San Antonio Gay & Lesbian Yellow Pages, 2005-2006 (Box 3, Item 29)
  - New Orleans Gay & Lesbian Yellow Pages, 2005-2006 (Box 3, Item 30)
  - Gay and Lesbian Yellow Pages, Summer 2006 (Box 3, Item 31)
  - Gay and Lesbian Yellow Pages, 1999 (Box 3, Item 32)
  - Gay and Lesbian Yellow Pages, 1998 (Box 3, Item 33)
  - Gay and Lesbian Yellow Pages, 1997 (Box 3, Item 34)
  - Gay and Lesbian Yellow Pages, 1996 (Box 3, Item 35)
  - Pride 03 Pamphlet (Box 3, Item 36)
  - Pride 05 Pamphlet (Box 3, Item 37)
  - Pride 01 Pamphlet (Box 3, Item 38)
  - Pride 06 Pamphlet (Box 3, Item 39)
  - Pride 07 Pamphlet (Box 3, Item 40)
  - Pride 08 Pamphlet (Box 3, Item 41)
  - Pride 12 Pamphlet (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Photographs - Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Photographs - “Our Yara, E20” (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Photographs - “Sausalits, Alcatraz, Homes + Trolley E6” (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Photographs - E8 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Photographs - “Meadowood, May 20, 1994” (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Photographs - “5294 (640ASA) Rest of Ruby’s B’day + Summer + Sheilah 1987” (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Photographs - “E16 #13 Alcatraz” (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Photographs - “E10 45/7+14” (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Photographs - “My 50th Party + Mary + Barbara Holy Union E5” (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Photographs - “91835 12-26 Butler, L Jo Anne old church +Mikies 1st memorial E11” (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Photographs - “E8” (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Photographs - “Mike’s Family + Ferry Ride” (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Photographs - “#21 + 26 Mikie in Alabama, by Stream, Mikie + I @ a Church function” (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Photographs - MCCR 1997 2000 Folder 1 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Photographs - Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Photographs - “Acapulco Christmas-New Year 1965-1966 For Diana 14 YB6” (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Photographs - “Mikie’s Memorial Stuff Pic out for my “passport” picture” (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Photographs - “Snowland + Angel Falls/Utah” (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Photograph Album removed from Box 73 L.Butler (Box 4, Folder 19-20)
  - Photograph Album removed from Box 73 L.Butler - Wedding (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Photographs - “E4 Missouri St. Fain Hou” (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Photographs - “Missouri St. Aquafest” (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Photographs - “E3 Sandi, Patti, Mikie + Me” (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Father John McNeil Tape (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - F1 Mike portrait (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - AIDS Memorial Quilt Certificate of Authenticity (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Weekly Memos John W. Gill, 1988-1993 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Committee Meetings, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Board Meetings, 1987-1994 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Board Meetings, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Board Meetings, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Committees Miscellaneous (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Committee Meetings, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Committee Meetings, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Committee Meetings, 1987-1990 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Committee Meetings, 1996-2001 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - The 12th General Conference (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Board of Elders Report (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Proposed Budget, 1986-1987 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - The 11th General Conference (Box 5, Folder 14-15)
  - General Conference 12, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - General Conference 6, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - General Conference 8, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - General Conference 10, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 19-21)
  - General Conference, 1981-1982 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Binder 1 Folder 1 Charities and Foundation Board Meetings (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Binder 1 Folder 2 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Binder 1 Folder 3 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Binder 2 Folder 1 Memos and Correspondence (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Binder 2 Folder 2 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Binder 3 Folder 1 Miscellaneous Foundation Paperwork (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Binder 3 Folder 2 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Binder 3 folder 3 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Binder 3 folder 4 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Security Report 2 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Security Report 3 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Committees/Organizations (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Family Care Team (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - General Correspondence, 1981-1982 (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
  - Samaritan Theological Institute (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - General Conference 5, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - General Conference 16, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - General Conference 13, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - ALERT (AIDS Legislation, Equalization, Research and Treatment) (UFMCC) (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - The Gay Christian Journal (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Board of Directors Binder 1 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Board of Directors Binder 2 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Board of Directors Binder 3 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - MCC Home Groups Binder (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Dealing With Depression Binder (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous Papers (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Budget and Financial Reports, 1974-1976 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Budget and Financial Reports, 1977-1979 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Budget and Financial Reports, 1980-1981 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Budget and Financial Reports, 1984-1987 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Budget and Financial Reports, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Budget and Financial Reports, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Budget and Financial Reports, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Budget and Financial Reports, 1998 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Budget and Financial Reports, 1999 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Budget and Financial Reports, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Budget and Financial Reports, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Home Study Groups (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Group 1 Materials (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Group 3 Materials (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Group 4 Materials (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Group 7 Week 6 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Group 14 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Group 15 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Group 16 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Group 17 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Group 19 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Group 6 Session 2 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Group 6 Session 5 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Group 8 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Group 9 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Group 7 Session 4 Part 1 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Group Posters 1 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Group 11 (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Group 12 Week 5 (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Group 13 (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Smoking Policy Ballots (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - Smoking Ballots 1990 (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - Security Reports 1 (Box 8, Folder 33)
  - Mobley, Carol (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - RMCC- Mobley, Carol (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Twogood, Dick (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Lasher, Ralph (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Student Clergy Classes (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Photographs (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Leadership Training (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Brochures (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Advertising (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Habitat for Humanity Superbuild, 2003 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - News Articles Gay Culture/Lifestyle (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Clergy Folder 1 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Clergy Folder 2 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Financial (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Fundraising (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Empowerment for Living (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Excel (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Archive 2000 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Archives and Library (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Board of Directors (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - World AIDS Day 2002 Mark Unbehagen (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Revision (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Special Services Folder 1 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Special Services Folder 2 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Stole Project (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Films
    - Balloons and Steve & Ed's party 7/4/78 (Item 1)
    - Texas Renaissance 1978 - Festival (Item 2)
      Montgomery ,TX
    - Texas Renaissance Festival, 1977 (Item 3)
    - T.R. Picnic, July 16, 1978 (Item 4)
    - POOR J S #1 1975-77 (Item 5)
    - POORS #s 2 (Item 6)
    - Numbers #5 Fall 1977 (Item 7)
      Lee @ Nautilus, Hitchhiker Safeway Sweeper - Joe Ringland and Solar Installers Skateboard #s
    - Numbers #2 (Item 8)
      Counselor, Kroger Center, In Car @ Milby PK, Tatooed, Pictures, See + Wave, Football, Palm Tree Trim
    - Numbers ? Fall 1975 (Item 9)
      H. H., Wavers & Lookers W.D.C., Milby Park Tsn Blond w/ Necklass Hunky blond(s) @ My 7-11
    - Numbers #6 (Item 10)
    - Number #3 Fall 76 Spring 77 (Item 11)
      The Hulk Married w/ Pipe Post Hole Digger
    - Number 4 Summer 1977 - Fall 1977 (Item 12)
      Cute Boxy #'s - Buccaneer Collee Green - HYBL + Viking Bee, Super BL @ Mt. Vernon, Fuzzy Blond off Gemini
    - Angels cheerleader tryouts, November 1978 (Item 13)
    - Gayday Pride San Francisco 1981 (Item 14)
    - Hawaii #'s (Item 15)
      Dated probably 80-81 -ldc
  - Audiocassette tapes
    - MCCR Sanctuary Choir - God with Us (Item 1)
    - Rev. Elder troy Perry “The Gospel According to MCCR” (Item 2-3)
    - San Francisco Gay Men’s Chorus (Item 4)
    - Sun 9-11 Coast Mass Choruses “Whitman Cantata” Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center NYC 1982 (Item 5)
    - New York, New York A Broadway Extravaganza with the New York Gay Men’s Chorus (Item 6)
    - A: Foxglove Woman, B: La Cage Aux Folles (Item 7)
    - A: A Lesbian Concentrate, B: Marge Adam - songwriter (Item 8)
- Eugene Harrington Collection
  - Plaques and Awards (Ovs box 10-11, Item 1)